AMANDEEP RATHEE

Data Scientist • Kaggle Expert

+1-984-245-5133 amandeep.rathee@duke.edu

www.linkedin.com/in/arathee2

Profile Summary

Accomplished data science consultant with deep expertise in machine learning and AI for computer vision and natural language processing. Successful track record of building top-rated online data science courses. Quick learner and an avid Kaggler with an all-time rank within the top 0.5% among all users.

EDUCATION

· Duke University, Durham, NC

Master in Interdisciplinary Data Science; GPA: 3.7/4.0

August 2019 - May 2021

Relevant coursework: Data to Decision, Statistical Modeling, Machine Learning, Data Visualization, Text Analyses and Data Ethics.

· Visvesvaraya Technological University, Bengaluru, India

Bachelor of Engineering in Computer Science and Engineering; GPA: 71/100

August 2013 - June 2017

Relevant coursework: Data Structures in C, Design and Analysis of Algorithms, Operations Research, Discrete Mathematics, UNIX Programming, Database Systems, Web Programming, Software Engineering and Testing.

SKILLS

- Languages: Python, R, SQL, Java, C++, MATLAB, Javascript, HTML CSS
- Tools: Git, LTpX, UNIX, Tableau, pandas, numpy, matplotlib, seaborn, keras, scikit-learn, tidyverse, caret
- Data Analysis: Regression Analysis, Hypothesis Testing, ANOVA, Hierarchical Modeling, A/B Testing, Data Visualization
- Machine Learning: Regression, Decision Trees, Bagging, Boosting, Support Vector Machines, Deep Neural Networks, CNNs, RNNs, LSTMs, GRUs, GANs, Clustering Analysis

EMPLOYMENT

Data Science Intern

Durham, NC

Center for Genomics and Computational Biology, Duke University

November 2019 - April 2020

- Building an open-source R package that computes mutual-exclusivity and semantic similarity among various traits in different species using ontology-based data. Project is NSF-funded and is a collaborative effort with three other universities in US.
- Data Science Content Strategist

upGrad Education Privated Limited

Bengaluru and Mumbai, India

July 2017 - May 2019

- Course Content Creation: Conceptualized and implemented learning goals, lesson plans, assessments and programming
 assignments that improved course ratings of the *Data Science* and *Machine Learning & AI* courses by 15% and job placement rate
 of students of the programs by 133%.
- Machine Learning & AI Courses: Created modules on deep neural networks, machine learning, natural language processing and Bayesian networks that increased revenue of this one-year online program by \$500,000 and helped it become #1 in India.
- Data Science Courses: Built high-quality data science courses through collaboration with professors, subject matter experts, product managers, and editing and tech teams, and drove the net promoter score from +25% to +60% in under a year as a result.
- Leveraged knowledge in data analysis, data visualization, and machine learning by working on projects such as *Telecom Churn Analyses*, *Patient Readmission Prediction*, *Neural Network Story Generator* and *Email Spam Detection*.

• Data Science Consultant

Upwork Global, Inc.

October 2016 - June 2017

• Deployed data science projects such as *Gesture Recognition, Server Downtime Predictor* and *Credit Card Fraud Detector* with an average project rating of 4.97/5 for clients around the globe in computer vision, IT and finance.

PERSONAL PROJECTS

- **Kaggle:** Ranked #33 among 100,000+ data science practitioners on Kaggle as a result of winning one gold, one silver and seven bronze medals by sharing insightful analyses using open datasets.
- Playstation vs Xbox: Conducted statistical analysis to determine that PlayStation games sell 30% more than Xbox games.
- **Sentiment Analysis:** Analyzed public opinion on Demonetization a highly controversial currency ban that happened in India in 2016 using Twitter API, and found that 50% of the tweets were neutral, 30% were in favor and 20% were against the ban.
- **H1B Visa Analyses:** Visualized the trend in the number of H1B visa issued under the Trump administration across different industries and found out that H1B visa rejections are on a rise since 2016.
- Socio-economic Development Index: Created an index to rank the districts of Odisha (India) by examining socio-economic factors using the government's open data to highlight the underdeveloped regions of the state.